<sect1 id="embedded-metadata">
  <title>Embedded Metadata</title>
  <para> 
   <emphasis>How do we add structured data to an existing document or file?</emphasis>
  </para>

  <sect2><title>Context</title>
  <para>There are two related aspects to this pattern</para>
  <para>Firstly, many web sites that are using frameworks or content management systems that 
  are either difficult to customize or are operated by organizations that have little or no in-house 
  technical staff. How can these sites be updated, with a minimum of effort, to support publishing of 
  structured data?</para>
  <para>Secondly, documents or files may be shared and copied across the web. This can result in a broken connection 
  between the document and it's metadata which might only be available from the source website. How 
  can the metadata be made available to anyone discovering a copy or mirror of the document?</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Solution</title>
  <para>Embed the structured data directly in the document itself rather than, or in addition to, publishing that 
  data separately.</para>
  <para>The most common scenario here is instrumenting an existing webpage to add some "semantic markup" that will enable 
  a client to extract data directly from the HTML source. This typically involves changing just the templates used ot 
  generate the web pages. By changing a small number of resources, it becomes possible to quickly and easily publish 
  data about a large number of resources.</para>
  <para>A less common scenario involves embedding data within a different document format. Typically this relies on 
  using an existing extension mechanism that has been defined for that format. A tool may then inspect the file directly 
  to discover the metadata or a link to its location.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Example(s)</title>
  <para>At the time of writing there are a number of competing proposals for embedding metadata in XHTML/HTML documents, 
  including RDFa, microdata and microformats. RDFa can also be used to embedded metadata in other XML formats</para>
  <para>Options vary for embedding metadata in other formats, but <ulink linkend="http://www.adobe.com/products/xmp/">Adobe XMP</ulink> 
  provides an option that can be used in a variety of formats.</para>
  
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Discussion</title>
  <para>Embedding metadata into existing resources, rather than requring changes to how content and data is published 
  to the web is often much easier to achieve. At the time of writing there are a number of competing approaches for 
  embedding metadata in XHTML/HTML. These typically offer the same basic features but vary in how much they require specific 
  markup extensions in the original document.</para>
  <para>While it can be very easy to quickly instrument a website with embedded metadata, the requirement to introduce all 
  data into the same template means that it can become awkward to manage the competing concerns: e.g. clean, well-structured markup 
  for styling and presentation, versus rich, detailed, semantic markup for machines. For more complex use cases its may be better to 
  simply publish the metadata separately, or embedded only a subset of the data with links to additional resources.</para>  
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Related</title>
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem><link linkend="primary-topic-autodiscovery">Primary Topic Autodiscovery</link></listitem>
  <listitem><link linkend="see-also">See Also</link></listitem>  
  </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

</sect1>
