<sect1 id="hierarchical-uris">
  <title>Hierarchical URIs</title>
  <para> 
   <emphasis>How should URIs be assigned to a group of resources that form a natural hierarchy?</emphasis>
  </para>

  <sect2><title>Context</title>
  <para>It is often the case that a collection of resources may form a natural hierarchy. E.g. the chapters within a book, or the departments within an organization. Reflecting this strict hierarchy within the URI structure makes those URIs more hackable allowing users/developers to "navigate" up the hierarchy by pruning the URI.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Solution</title>
  <para>Where a natural hierarchy exists between a set of resources use <link linkend="patterned-uris">Patterned URIs</link> that conform to the following pattern:</para>
<para><code>:collection/:item/:sub-collection/:item</code></para>
<para>E.g. in a system which is publishing data about individual books and their chapters, we might use the following identifier for chapter 1 of a specific book:</para>
<para><code>/books/12345/chapters/1</code></para>
<para>The <code>/chapters</code> URI will naturally reflect to the collection of all chapters within a specific book. The <code>/books</code> URI maps to the collection of all books within a system, etc.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Example(s)</title>
  <para>The discogs dataset in dataincubator uses hierarchical uris of the form:</para>
<para><code>http://discogs.dataincubator.org/release/22530/track/1-01</code></para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Discussion</title>
<para>This technique is best suited to scenarios where the items in the sub-collections (chapters) are always associated with a single parent item. Other relationships might exist, e.g. the chapter may be included in another but the chapter is always associated with at least one book: they do not exist in isolation. In circumstances where this doesn't hold true, then it is best to just use simple Patterned URIs.</para>
<para>The same applies to circumstances where the hierarchy may change over time.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Related</title>
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem><link linkend="patterned-uris">Patterned URIs</link></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
