<sect1 id="label-everything">
  <title>Label Everything</title>
  <para> 
   <emphasis>How can we ensure that every resource has a basic human-readable name?</emphasis>
  </para>

  <sect2><title>Context</title>
  <para>A dataset may have a number of different entities, some of which are simple, e.g. people or organizations, whereas others are 
  more conceptual or complex, e.g. an observation made at a particular point in time, under specific conditions. It may not always be clear 
  to a developer, or a user exploring a graph in a browser, what a particular resource represents</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Solution</title>
  <para>Ensure that every resource in a dataset has an <code>rdfs:label</code> property</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Example(s)</title>
  <programlisting>
   <![CDATA[
ex:Book
  rdfs:label "War and Peace".
  
ex:WeatherObservation
  rdfs:label "Rainfall measurement from Weather Station 1 recorded by Bob on 17th August 2011"; 
  ex:rainfall 50;
  ex:date "2011-08-17"^^xsd:date
  ex:location ex:WeatherStation1;
  ex:experimenter ex:Bob.  
   ]]>
  </programlisting>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Discussion</title>
  <para>The <code>rdfs:label</code> property is a useful generic property for labelling any type of resource. By using this generic property to label 
  any resource we can ensure that applications can easily discover a useful default label for a specific resource using a well-known property. This is 
  particularly useful for supporting browsing of a dataset, as a browser can look for a default label. Developers can also use the label to assist in 
  debugging queries or exploring a dataset. 
  </para>
  <para>
  Client applications may not always wish to use a provided label instead preferring to construct them based on other criteria. 
  The <link linkend="preferred-label">Preferred Label</link> pattern recommends using the <code>skos:prefLabel</code> 
  property to communicate to clients a preferred label specified by the data publisher.  
  </para>
  <para>
  In some cases both a <code>rdfs:label</code> and a <code>skos:prefLabel</code> (or other specific labelling property such as <code>dcterms:title</code>) 
  might be provided for the same resource. The content of the labels may differ reflecting the slightly different semantics of each property, e.g the 
  <code>rdfs:label</code> might be longer or more descriptive than a shorter <code>skos:prefLabel</code>. If both label properties are provided with the 
  same content, then this is an example of the <link linkend="materialize-inferences">Materialize Inference</link> pattern: <code>skos:prefLabel</code> is
  a specialization of <code>rdfs:label</code>.  
  </para>
  <para>The importance of applying labels to Linked Data, as well as evidence for the poor adoption of this practice, is given in a paper called "Labels in the Web of Data" by Basil Ell, Denny Vrandečić, and Elena Simperl.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Related</title>
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem><link linkend="preferred-label">Preferred Label</link></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Further Reading</title>
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem><ulink linkend="http://www.aifb.kit.edu/images/c/c0/LabelsInTheWebOfData.pdf">Labels in the Web of Data (Paper)</ulink></listitem>
  <listitem><ulink linkend="http://videolectures.net/iswc2011_ell_labels/">Labels in the Web of Data (Video Lecture + Slides)</ulink></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

</sect1>
