<sect1 id="shared-keys">
  <title>Shared Keys</title>
  <para> 
   <emphasis>How do we simplify the inter-linking of datasets?</emphasis>
  </para>

  <sect2><title>Context</title>
  <para>It is common to carry out inter-linking of datasets as a separate activity following the initial modelling and data conversion exercises have been completed. How can the final stage of inter-linking be simplified?</para>
<para>
It is also common that within a specific domain there will be a set of non-web identifiers that are standardised across different applications and publishers. How can the inter-linking of those datasets be simplified, encouraging convergence on web identifiers?
</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Example(s)</title>
  <para>The BBC have created URIs for artists that are algorithmically related to the MusicBrainz URIs, as they use a simple Shared Key: the MusicBrainz ID. Any application that already uses a MusicBrainz ID can therefore easily inter-link with either source.
</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Solution</title>
  <para>Create <link linkend="patterned-uris">Patterned URIs</link> by applying the <link linkend="natural-keys">Natural Keys</link> pattern, but prefer public, standard identifiers rather than internal system specific codes.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Rationale</title>
  <para>Predictable URIs structures make it easy for application developers and toolkits to build URIs from simple templates. By using URIs that are constructed from public identifiers, that already have scope outside of the immediate application, it increases the ease with which inter-linking can take place. For example, the pattern may avoid the need to look-up URIs in a SPARQL endpoint, allowing a developer to simplify use a URI template.</para>
<para>
The Shared Keys pattern is best suited to situations where the shared identifiers is stable and rarely changes.
</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Related</title>
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem><link linkend="patterned-uris">Patterned URIs</link>></listitem>
  <listitem><link linkend="natural-keys">Natural Keys</link></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
