<sect1 id="smushing">
  <title>Smushing</title>
  <para> 
   <emphasis>How do we merge data about resources that may not be consistently identified?</emphasis>
  </para>

  <sect2><title>Context</title>
  
  <para>It will often be the case that different data publishers have used different identifiers for the same resource. In some cases 
  there may be direct <link linkend="equivalence-links">Equivalence Links</link> between resources. In others their equivalence might 
  be inferred based on other data, e.g. common properties.</para>
  <para>How can we merge statements made about these distinct resources into a single description?</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Solution</title>
  <para>Apply the technique of "smushing" to manipulate an RDF graph containing the descriptions of each of the resources. Broadly a smushing 
  algorithm will consist of the following steps:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>Decide on the URI for the resource that will hold the final description, i.e. the <emphasis>target resource</emphasis> -- this could be one randomly selected from 
  available URIs, or one from a local dataset</listitem>
  <listitem>Identify all <emphasis>equivalent resources</emphasis> -- i.e. by finding <link linkend="equivalence-links">Equivalence Links</link>
  such as <code>owl:sameAs</code> statements, or by property values that indicate that two resources are similar 
  (e.g. Inverse Functional Properties, see below).</listitem>
  <listitem>Iterate over the <emphasis>equivalent resources</emphasis> and for each RDF statement for which it is the <emphasis>subject</emphasis>, assert a new 
  statement with the same predicate and object but using the <emphasis>target resource</emphasis> as the subject</listitem>
  <listitem>Iterate over the <emphasis>equivalent resources</emphasis> and for each RDF statement for which it is the <emphasis>object</emphasis>, assert a new 
  statement with the same subject and predicate but using the <emphasis>target resource</emphasis> as the object</listitem>  
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>The end result will be an modified RDF graph with all properties of the <emphasis>equivalent resources</emphasis> being "copied" to the 
  <emphasis>target resource</emphasis>. In addition, any references to the <emphasis>equivalent resources</emphasis> will also be made to the target 
  resource</para>
  <para>By applying this to all resources in a graph, the available data can be normalized into a consistent set of descriptions based on a known set of 
  resources. An application may then generate a <link linkend="bounded-description">Bounded Description</link> of any resource and guarantee that it 
  will include all available data</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Example(s)</title>
  <para>Assume we start with the following graph, which contains two equivalent resources, as defined by 
  an <code>owl:sameAs</code> link.</para>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
<http://example.com/product/6>
  rdfs:label "Camera";
  owl:sameAs <http://example.org/cameras/10>.

<http://example.org/cameras/10>
  ex:manufacturer <http://example.org/company/5>.

<http://example.org/company/5>.
  ex:manufactured <http://example.org/cameras/10>.

]]>
</programlisting>  
  <para>Assuming we want to collate all data around resources from <code>example.com</code>, we can apply smushing to create the 
  following graph:</para>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
<http://example.com/product/6>
  rdfs:label "Camera";
  owl:sameAs <http://example.org/cameras/10>;  
  ex:manufacturer <http://example.org/company/5>.
  
<http://example.org/cameras/10>
  ex:manufacturer <http://example.org/company/5>.

<http://example.org/company/5>.
  ex:manufactured <http://example.org/cameras/10>.
  ex:manufactured <http://example.com/product/6>.
]]>
</programlisting>  
  <para>We can also tidy up the graph to remove statements about the equivalent resources, leaving:</para>
<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
<http://example.com/product/6>
  rdfs:label "Camera";
  owl:sameAs <http://example.org/cameras/10>;  
  ex:manufacturer <http://example.org/company/5>.
  
<http://example.org/company/5>.
  ex:manufactured <http://example.com/product/6>.
]]>
</programlisting>  
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Discussion</title>
  <para>Smushing is essentially a process of inference: by using available data we create new statements. Any OWL reasoner will carry out 
  this kind of data merging automatically based on the available data and schema/ontology without the need for custom code. Applications that 
  are using a triple store that applies inferencing by default will not need to use this approach. However for applications that don't need a 
  full inferencing engine, or need only lightweight merging of data, then a custom smushing algorithm can achieve the same goal.</para>

  <para>There are several different variations on algorithm described above. For example, applications might vary in how they nominate the 
  <emphasis>target resource</emphasis>. Typically though this will be based on a preferred URI. Algorithms can also be divided into those that 
  preserve the original statements, e.g. so that the <emphasis>equivalent resources</emphasis> remain in the source RDF graph, or whether their statements 
  are removed from the graph to leave only a normalized description. Applications could also use <link linkend="named-graphs">Named Graphs</link> to 
  separately stored the "smushed" view of the data, preserving the original data in another graph or triple store.</para>

  <para>As noted above there are also several ways to identify equivalent resources. <link linkend="equivalence-links">Equivalence Links</link> are an obvious 
  approach. Other cues can also be used including the use of <ulink linkend="http://www.w3.org/TR/owl-ref/#InverseFunctionalProperty-def">Inverse Functional Properties</ulink>. 
  An inverse functional property is simply a property whose value uniquely identifies a resource, such as <link linkend="literal-keys">Literal Keys</link>.</para>
  <para>An application is also free to apply it's own rules about what consistutes "equivalence". For example an application may decide to merge together resources 
  with similar property values, even if those properties are not declared as Inverse Functional Properties. This allows for local customization of smushing 
  rules, but runs the risk of generating false positives. One way to apply these custom rules is to use local <link linkend="schema-annotation">Schema Annotations</link> to 
  declare specific properties as being equivalent. This has the benefit of working with both custom code and OWL reasoners.</para>
  
  <para>Smushing is often used to normalize an RDF graph resulting from a <link linkend="follow-your-nose">Follow Your Nose</link> approach to 
  data discovery</para>
  
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Related</title>
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem><link linkend="equivalence-links">Equivalence Links</link></listitem>
  <listitem><link linkend="follow-your-nose">Follow Your Nose</link></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Further Reading</title>
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem><ulink linkend="http://wiki.foaf-project.org/w/Smushing">Smushing</ulink></listitem>
  <listitem><ulink linkend="http://www.w3.org/wiki/RdfSmushing">RDF Smushing</ulink></listitem>  
  <listitem><ulink linkend="http://www.ldodds.com/blog/2005/08/smushing-algorithms/">Smushing Algorithms</ulink></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
