<sect1 id="topic-relation">
  <title>Topic Relation</title>
  <para> 
   <emphasis>How can a web page or document be associated with a resource?</emphasis>
  </para>

  <sect2><title>Context</title>
  <para>There is often a need to associate a resource with a page or document that provides further, human-readable content about the resource. This information may often be present in a content management system or dataset as "further reading" links. How can these relations be published as RDF, clearly identifying the relationship between the document and the resource being described?</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Solution</title>
  <para>Use the <code>foaf:topic</code> and/or <code>foaf:primaryTopic</code> relationships to associate a resource with a page(s) in which it is featured or discussed</para>
  </sect2>


  <sect2><title>Example(s)</title>
  <para>In a dataset describing Paris, some additional further reading links may be available:</para>

<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
<http://www.example.org/place/Paris> a ex:Place;
   skos:prefLabel "Paris"@fr.

<http://travel.example.com/blog/a-paris-guide>
   foaf:primaryTopic <http://www.example.org/place/Paris>.

<http://travel.example.com/blog/top-europe-cities>
   foaf:topic <http://www.example.org/place/Paris>.
]]>
</programlisting>

  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Rationale</title>
  <para>There will always be a mix of unstructured documents and structured data on the Semantic Web. There are many kinds of relations that could be expressed between a document and a resource, but a very common relation is one of categorisation, e.g. identifying when a document or page has a specific focus or theme. The FOAF topic terms, <code>foaf:topic</code> and <code>foaf:primaryTopic</code> provide a means to link a document directly with a resource which features as a topic in that document.
  </para>
  <para>Other vocabularies provide similar related properties that may be more useful in some scenarios. For example Dublin Core defines the <code>dc:subject</code> property, but this is best used to relate a document to an entry in a controlled vocabulary, e.g. a subject heading, rather than a "real world" resource.</para>
  <para>Because the Topic Relation pattern involves making statements about other resources on the web, it is an application of the <link linkend="annotation">Annotation</link> pattern.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2><title>Related</title>
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem><link linkend="annotation">Annotation</link></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

</sect1>
